<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/howto.xsl"?>
<guide created="06/16/2007">
    <author email="john.mcfarlane@rockfloat.com">John McFarlane</author>
    <abstract title="How to setup a brand new Windows computer">
        This document will help you setup your new computer properly
        from the very beginning, with the hopes that this will not
        elimintate, but help mitigate security related problems down the
        line (viruses/popups). Hardening a computer against security
        related threats is no easy task and this document hardly
        scratches the surface... but hopefully it will give a place to
        start.
    </abstract>
    <convention>This howto currently only applies to Windows XP</convention>
    <convention>You do hate popups... don't you?</convention>
    <change date="06/16/2006 @18:00">Initial creation</change>

    <action title="Make sure your computer isn't on the internet" anchor="safe">
        The very first thing you want to do is <em>keep it OFF of the internet</em>
        until it's ready.  That means if you already plugged it into your dsl/cable
        box, unplug it.  You want your computer to be a bit more "hardened"
        before you subject it to the nasty world wide web.
        <link uri="http://news.com.com/Study%3A+Unpatched+PCs+compromised+in+20+minutes/2100-7349_3-5313402.html?part=r">
            REFERENCE
        </link>
        <p>
            For all you Dilbert fans out there, the assumption here is that
            you're not reading this on your new computer.  Use something
            else!
        </p>
    </action>
    
    <action title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
        A bit of background is probably the best way to get started.
        <p>
            Windows has alot of default settings that make things
            "easy", but they make your computer more vulnerable.
            As you read thru this document you'll learn how to change a
            few of these default settings to help make your new computer
            more secure.
        </p>
        <p>
            You can't 100% protect any computer that's connected to the
            internet I don't care how hard you try... the goal is simply
            to minimize it. With safe practices and a decently hardened
            computer I think it's realistic to expect approximately 3
            years of life before you have to have it rebuilt (not
            replaced, just "redone" by someone).
        </p>
    </action>

    <action title='What is a "unprivileged user"?' anchor="unprivileged_user">
        <b>Answer</b>: A user that only belongs to the <lt>users</lt> group.
        <p>
            Currently your computer has one account: <lt>Administrator</lt>
            which happens to be a member of the <lt>Administrator</lt>
            group (Windows security is managed by users and groups).
            <image uri="win_login_default.png" />
            This means that <i>this</i> user or member(s) of <i>this</i> group
            have full rights on your computer.
        </p>

        <p>
            Depending on how the manufacturer setup your computer it
            might give you an opportunity to create additional users.
            It's important to understand that these users will also be a
            member of the Administrator group.
        </p>
        <p>
            This is a security risk, because if "something" tries to do
            something bad  to your computer, they do so
            <em>
                under the privileges of the currently logged in user
            </em>.
            Another words, if I'm a virus... I'm going to hope you are using
            an administrative account.
        </p>
        <p>
            The solution is to make sure you have a user that is not a member
            of the <lt>administrators</lt> group and always log into the computer using
            this account.  This will drastically make your computer safer
            against attack, though you will have to deal with the hastle of
            having to temporarily log in as <lt>Adminstrator</lt> to do
            things like:
            <list>
                <element>Install software</element>
                <element>Change the clock time</element>
                <element>Write to files outside of: <lt>My Documents</lt></element>
                <element>Change system settings</element>
                <element>Configure hardware or networking</element>
            </list>
            <tip>
                To summarize: logging in as an unpriveledged user will
                make your computer much more resistant to spyware and viruses.
            </tip>
        </p>
        <image uri="win_groups_default.png" />
    </action>
    
    <action title="Create an unprivileged user" anchor="create_unprivileged_user">
        Follow these steps to create an unpriviledged user:
        <list>
            <element>
                Open the <lt>Control Panel</lt> from the start menu
                <image uri="win_startmenu_default.png" />                
            </element>
            <element>
                Select <lt>Administrative Tools</lt> from the Control Panel
                <image uri="win_control_panel.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                Select <lt>Computer Management</lt> from Administrative Tools
                <image uri="win_administrative_tools.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                Expand <lt>Local Users and Groups</lt>
                <image uri="win_computer_management.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                If you have created any users already you will see them here
                <image uri="win_users_default.png" />
                Above is what most fresh installations of Windows XP will look
                like.
            </element>
            <element>
                Right click on <lt>Users</lt> and select <lt>New User...</lt>
                <image uri="win_user_add.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                Fill out the form, mine looks like this:
                <image uri="win_user_add_form2.png" />
                When finished click <lt>Create</lt>.
            </element>
            <element>
                Right click on the user you just created and select
                <lt>Properties</lt>
                <image uri="win_user_manage.png" />
                Then select the <lt>Member Of</lt> tab
                <image uri="win_user_preferences.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                Take note that the user is <b>only</b> a member of the
                Users group
                <image uri="win_user_preferences2.png" />
            </element>
        </list>
    </action>
    
    <action title="Log in using the new unpriviledged user" anchor="log_in">
        The new user will show up in the menu when you log out or restart
        your computer, mine looks like this:
        <image uri="win_login_newuser.png" />
        Select your shiney new user and enter the password
        <image uri="win_login_newuser2.png" />
        <tip>
            The only time you should use the Administrator account is if you
            need to install software, change the clock... or other
            administrative type tasks.
        </tip>
    </action>
    
    <action title="What you need to know about software" anchor="software_info">
        <b>Begin rambling, just to brainstorm ideas...</b>
        <p>
            Software on your computer is installed in different ways.
            Some is installed by the manufacturer (Dell, HP, Gateway),
            some is installed by the operating system or it's
            subsystems. Windows update is a good example of this, as
            it's sort of part of the operating system, and it installs
            stuff for you (patches and things). The rest is usually
            installed by you. Here's where it gets important. Software
            is usually installed by double clicking on a setup file such
            as "setup.exe". Usually this is followed by a series of
            prompts which some people referr to as a "wizard". Either
            way the result is that your system has new files and
            settings which represent the software you just installed.
        </p>
        <p>
            What's confusing is when software gets installed... but how
            it got there is a mystery. For example, let's say you have
            "Gator" installed on your computer and it's driving you
            nuts. You likely don't remember installing it, nor anyone
            else. It could have been installed several different ways
            but I do happen to know that installing "Comet Cursor" I
            think it was, would also install "Gator" without really
            telling you. This is extremely significant because it
            illustrates that when you install something, it might do
            things that you don't expect. It's very important to think
            before you install something, because clicking on that
            "setup.exe" file ultimately lets the person who wrote the
            software have complete control over your system for the
            duration that it's being installed.
        </p>
        <p>
            Below you'll find a list of software packages that are considered
            <i><em>at least by me</em></i> to be professional and trustworthy.
        </p>
        
    </action>
    
    <action title="Recommended software" anchor="recommended_software">
        Here is a list of software packages that you should migrate to:
        <table>
            <header>
                <col>Current</col>
                <col>Recommended</col>
                <col>Reason</col>
            </header>
            <row>
                <col>Internet Explorer</col>
                <col>Mozilla Firefox</col>
                <col>
                    Internet Explorer is the single most dangerous piece
                    of software you can use. It has a terrible history
                    for security problems, some of which to this day
                    have yet to be addressed by Microsoft. Additionally
                    it's extremely outdated and is lacking features that
                    most other browsers have. Mozilla Firefox is an
                    excellent software package used by millions of
                    people. It has an excellent feature set, is very
                    secure.
                    <link uri="http://www.forbes.com/home/ebusiness/2004/10/04/cx_pp_1004mondaymatchup.html">REFERENCE</link>,
                    <link uri="http://www.securityfocus.com/columnists/249">REFERENCE</link>,
                    <link uri="http://reviews.cnet.com/4520-3513_7-6333507-1.html">REFERENCE</link>
                </col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>Outlook</col>
                <col>Mozilla Thunderbird</col>
                <col>
					 Thunderbird is not as integrated with the Windows Operating system and
					 thus is not as vulnerable to
					 <i>windows operating system</i>
					 vulnerabilities. Thunderbird is designed to be solid from a security
					 perspective with things like defaultly not downloading images, spam and
					 phishing detection. It also supports pretty much everything you'd ever
					 need when it comes to email, though it does not [<i>yet</i>]
					 support calendering like Outlook does with Microsoft Exchange Server.
                </col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>Microsoft Office</col>
                <col>OpenOffice</col>
                <col>
                    Microsoft Office is a huge target. OpenOffice is an
                    alternative product that has an impressive set of
                    features and has (so far) a very good security history.
                    Additionally it has a few unique features that are really
                    nice:
                    <list>
                        <element>Support for one click export to PDF</element>
                        <element>
                        Full support for MS formats, meaning you can
                        still use your doc/xls/ppt files.
                        </element>
                        <element>
                            Impress (like powerpoint) documents can be
                            exported to flash which really comes in
                            handy
                        </element>
                    </list>   
                    Mark my word... in time the educational system will make
                    ODF the default file format, which is the standard in OpenOffice.
                    <link uri="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenDocument_debate">REFERENCE</link>
                </col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>Instant messenger clients: AOL, Yahoo, MSN</col>
                <col>Trillian/Gaim</col>
                <col>
                    You can replace all of your instant messenger
                    software with one , and it works very well.
                    <link uri="http://gaim.sourceforge.net/security/">
                        REFERENCE
                    </link>
                </col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>Windows Media Player</col>
                <col>Winamp and VLC</col>
                <col>Windows media player is also a target for malware.  Using
                wimamp and VLC keeps you under the radar a bit.</col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>Microsoft Hotmail</col>
                <col>Yahoo Mail or Google Gmail</col>
                <col>
                    Hotmail doesn't exactly have a strong record when it
                    comes to security
                </col>
            </row>
            <row>
            	<col>N/A</col>
            	<col>7zip</col>
            	<col>
            		There's nothing really insecure about the default
            		Windows XP zip utility, it just doesn't work very
            		well.  7zip is tiny, free - and is excellent.
            	</col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>Mcafee/Norton</col>
                <col>ClamWin</col>
                <col>
                    There's nothing wrong with either Norton or Macfee,
                    though they do tend to be kinda, busy? and often
                    times people don't pay for the software after the
                    trial expires and they wind up without any
                    protection. ClamWin is a port of ClamAV and is free
                    for use.
                </col>
            </row>
            <row>
                <col>RealPlayer</col>
                <col>Real Alternative</col>
                <col>
                    There's nothing wrong with RealPlayer really from a
                    security perspective, but it's so annoying how it
                    tries to take over.
                </col>
            </row>
        </table>
        It's also important to note that all of the software packages
        recommended above are open source, meaning that they are free
        for use, and are actively supported by the community.

        <p>
            Since <b>NOT</b> using Internet Explorer is probably the best thing
            you can do to keep your computer safe, let's go thru how to
            install Firefox:
        </p>
        <list>
            <element>
                Remember you need to log in as <lt>Administrator</lt> to do this.
            </element>
            <element>
                Use Internet Explorer (it's all you have right now) to download
                the installation file from
                <link uri="http://www.mozilla.com/firefox/">
                    http://www.mozilla.com/firefox/
                </link>
                and click on the "Download Firefox" link.
                <image uri="win_download_firefox.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                When prompted, remember to <em>Always</em>
                "Save" the file. Never choose "Run".
                <image uri="win_download_dialog.png" />
                The file will defautly be placed on your desktop, so you know
                where to find it after it's finished downloading.
            </element>
            <element>
                Double click on the Firefox Setup executable file placed
                on your desktop to begin the installation.
                <image uri="win_firefox_install.png" />
                Follow the prompts, taking the defaults is just fine.
            </element>
            <element>
                When the installation is finished, it will place an icon
                on your desktop that you can use to start the application.
                If you like to use the <lt>Quicklaunch</lt> icons, it will
                be there also
            </element>
            <element>
                Ok, remembering our good practice here... if there's no other
                software to install:
                <p>
                    <em>
                        Remember to log out, and log back in as your
                        unpriviledged user!
                    </em>
                </p>
            </element>
        </list>
        
        
        
    </action>
    
    <action title="Patches and Windows Update" anchor="patches">
        Keeping Windows XP patched is extremely important for the
        security health of your PC. Luckily Microsoft does an excellent
        job of making this easy and reliable.
        <p>
            All you need to do is enable <lt>Windows Update</lt> to manage that
            for you.  But because this is a brand new computer, you need to 
            manually patch it.
        </p>
        <p>
            It's important to understand that <em>this should be the first
            time your computer has ever been plugged into the internet</em>
            and the goal is to get it patched as quickly as possible.
        </p>
        <list>
            <element>
                You need to be logged into your computer as the Administrator
                to install patches manually.
            </element>
            <element>
                Select <lt>Windows Update</lt> from the startup menu
                <image uri="win_startmenu_default.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                Internet Explorer will open, look for something like this
                <image uri="windows_update.png" />
                You want to click on the <lt>Express</lt> button to get high
                priority updates.
            </element>
            <element>
                You will be presented with a list of patches that need to be
                applied
                <image uri="windows_update3.png" />
                Click on <lt>Install Updates</lt> to install them.
            </element>
            <element>
                You will see the patches download and install...
                <image uri="windows_update_installing.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                When it's finished it will most likely prompt you to restart
                your computer.  Sometimes this isn't neccessary.
                <image uri="windows_update_restart.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                When your computer has finished rebooting, repeat this process
                over and over until you see this when looking for new updates:
                <image uri="windows_update_finished.png" />
               
            </element>
        </list>
        Now you need to configure Windows Update to run automaticaly, cuz
        if you're lazy like me you'll forget to keep up on it.
        <list>
            <element>
                Click on Windows Update from the start menu like you did before,
                and look toward the right this time
                <image uri="windows_update.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                If it says <lt>Turn on Automatic Updates</lt> then click on it
                and select a time that your computer is likely to be turned on.
                <image uri="win_automatic_updates.png" />
            </element>
            <element>
                 You're all finished, click <lt>OK</lt> and log in as your
                 unpriviledged user  :)
            </element>
        </list>
        
    </action>
    
    <action title="Harden Microsoft Internet Explorer" anchor="ie">
        Even though you shouldn't use IE, there are times when you will have to
        probably it.  For these situations, it should be hardened as much as
        possible.
        <list>
            <element>
                Install the Google toolbar as it will block popups.  This will
                limit the number of Phishing dialog boxes that will popup, which
                if clicked on could install malware of some kind.
            </element>
        </list>
    </action>
    
    <action title="Harden Firefox" anchor="firefox">
        Disable support for Java.  You can enable for each time you need it,
        as you need it.
    </action>
    
    <action title="Clean up startup programs in the registry" anchor="registry">
        Not sure what to include/not include, bug geezle HP boxes seem
        to come with alot of stuff.
    </action>
    
    <action title='Learn how to be a "smart surfer"' anchor="smart_surfer">
        Outline how to do the following:
        <list>
            <element>Downloading</element>
            <element>Clicking</element>
            <element>Email</element>
            <element>Phishing</element>
        </list>
    </action>
    
    <action title="Specific software settings" anchor="specific_software_settings">
        
    </action>
    
    <action title="Antivirus software" anchor="antivirus">
        
    </action>

    <!--
    <action title="" anchor="">
        <code></code>
    </action>
    -->
</guide>
