<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/howto.xsl"?>
<guide created="11/18/2005">
    <author email="john.mcfarlane@rockfloat.com">John McFarlane</author>
    <abstract title="Gentoo - portage usage, tips and tricks">
        This document outlines how to use portage to install things,
        and keep your setup current on patches.
    </abstract>
    
    <change date="11/18/2005 @ 10:00">Initial creation</change>
    
    <action title="Update your list of packages" anchor="dependancies">
        Before you ever install something on Gentoo you want to update
        your list of packages.  This is analgous to
        <literal>apt-get -update</literal>. Remember that this doesn't install
        any softare, rather it just updates information about packages:
        <br/>
        Perform the update:
        <code>root# emerge sync</code>
        I recommend running this via cron daily, that way it's always up to date.
    </action>
    
    <action title="Update your system - you don't want to get r00ted" anchor="update">
        Now that you have an up to date Portage tree, you want to update
        the actual softare on your system.
        <code>root# emerge -uDa world</code>
        Here's what that means:
        <list>
        	<element>emerge (install)</element>
        	<element><literal>u</literal> (update)</element>
        	<element><literal>D</literal> (deep, so dependancies are also used)</element>
        	<element><literal>a</literal> (ask permission before installing!)</element>
        </list>
        What you will see is a list of sofware that is about to be installed.
        Look thru the list and make sure you are comfortable with everything,
        and if so.... type <literal>y</literal> to go ahead and do it, otherwise
        type <literal>n</literal> to bail.
    </action>
    
    <action title="Check to see if any config files need to be updated" anchor="check_configs">
        Portage will automatically handle any trivial changes, but sometimes
        there are changes that you need to manage.
        <code>root# etc-update</code>
        Here's what you do next:
        <list>
        	<element>
        		Look at the list of configuration files it gives you.  Look
        		for any config files you care about, or recognize.  For example
        		if you run apache or php and there are config files related
        		to either, then manage these first.
        		<list>
        			<element>Type the number next to the config file</element>
        			<element>
        				example: <literal>4</literal>
        				This will select this particular config and present
        				you with a list of the differences (in less)
        			</element>
        			<element>Hit <literal>q</literal> to exit less</element>
        			<element>
        				Now you should see a menu asking what you want to do.
        				Pick...
        			</element>
        		</list>
        	</element>
        	<element>Once you've dealt with all config's that you care about
        		you can feel free to let the system take care of the rest.  Type
        		<literal>-3</literal> and it will go thru and replace each
        		config with the updated version.  For each one it will prompt
        		to delete the old version, go ahead and hit <literal>y</literal>
        		for each one.
        	</element>
        </list>
    </action>

    <!--
    <action title="" anchor="">
        <code></code>
    </action>
    -->    
</guide>
