<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/howto.xsl"?>
<guide created="09/27/2005">
    <author email="john.mcfarlane@rockfloat.com">John McFarlane</author>
    <abstract title="Microsoft - their software can be annoying sometimes">
        This document will show how to explain to someone that Microsoft
	has some annoying stuff goin on.
    </abstract> 
    <convention>This document assumes you prolly have an unhealthy degree of bias already</convention>
    <convention>So maybe my spelling/grammar isn't the best</convention>
    <change date="09/27/2005 @12:16">Initial creation</change>
            
    <action title="File name limitations" anchor="file_name_limitations">
    	The current NTFS filesystem has some messed up file name limitations. For example,
	on Windows XP examine the following:
	<code>
Valid file name:      ;.]-=(fo'$%@~)^o&amp;   fr.txt
Invalid file name:    .svn
	</code>
	What kind of sense does that make?
    </action>
    
    <action title="Default image type during cut and paste" anchor="bmp">
        Ever hit "print screen" and pasted into word? Yea, you get an awesome
	bitmap. Nothing funner than getting screenshots from users (each of which
	is 1.2m) in bitmap format filling up your inbox.
    </action>

    <action title="File renaming includes the file extension" anchor="f2">
        Have you ever hit F2, or right clicked "rename" and noticed that
	you have to select the name of the file with your mouse or keyboard
	before you can change it... else you need to type the extension again?
	I guess this one's prolly unreasonable, but I find it annoying.
    </action>
    
    <action title="Deleting an empty directory can take forever" anchor="rm">
        I've had times when it takes 30 seconds to delete an empty directory.
	A person could argue that my machine was unhealthy at the time, but geezle.
    </action>

    <action title="The default windows XP Start Menu" anchor="start_menu">
        Enough said.
    </action>

    <action title="Defragmentation, still?" anchor="defrag">
        NTFS still requires manual defrag?
    </action>

    <action title="Command line interface" anchor="dos">
        I know most would completely disagree with me here, but try to get
	alot of work done during an emergency over dialup (if that's all you've
	got) using the current cli. Word has it Vista might have something much
	improved.
    </action>

    <action title="Cannot write to file because it's being used by some process" anchor="lsof">
        It would be nice to have something to tell you what process is
	using the file.  Maybe <literal>lsof</literal> for Windows?
	I'm sure something's out there but I haven't seen it yet.
    </action>

    <action title="Back in the day I paid $1,000 for W2k server" anchor="w2kserver">
        I was having an install problems, so I called for support. The call was going to
	be $250 just to get someone on the line, and I just got back from the store spending
	1k?  That was annoying.
    </action>

    <action title="Hardware support (standard stuff, like nics)" anchor="hardware_support">
        A while ago I installed W2k3 Standard Server on an HP D530 (P4, year old maybe)
	and I could't get the network card to work:
	<literal>
	Broadcom NetXtreme Gigabit Ethernet for HP
	</literal>
	I'm sure I was doing something wrong, but it suddenly started working after I
	installed drivers from the manufacturer.  That's annoying to not have such
	a typical driver. What makes it even worse, I didn't have a cdrw or a floppy
	in the computer. Yes, I used a freeking USB floppy to get the driver on the
	computer. Just for kicks, I popped in a Knoppix disk and was surfing the net
	after one keystroke (enter). I know Windows has awesome support for the latest
	webcam or USB game or whatever, but this was W2k3 server, I just wanted the NIC
	work.
    </action>

    <action title="Visual Source Safe" anchor="vss">
        Come one, no way it's still this bad.
    </action>

    <action title="System recovery" anchor="recovery">
        I on several occasions have either had my machine fail to boot, or I've
	observed someone else in the same situation. What are you supposed to do
	if it won't boot? In fact, I think it was my W2k Server that I paid 1k
	for that wouldn't boot.
	<br/><br/>
	PS: The recovery console is not a valid solution
    </action>

    <action title="File system searching stinks" anchor="searching">
        There's not really a good way to search for files that have "bla"
	in the filename, and also contain the contents "wooo".
    </action>

    <action title="Task manager is not responding" anchor="task_manager">
        When you can't kill an application or process, please don't tell me
	the only resort is to reboot. Actually, there's a neat little program
	called kill.exe that works much of the time. Please include it by default,
	and provide something else when it also isn't able to stop something. It
	is really annoying to loose work you've done in autocad or somethign, because
	IE locked up.
    </action>

    <action title="Antivirus software slowing things down too much" anchor="antivirus">
        It's really frustrating when you are in the middle of composing an email or
	word processing document right when Mcafee/Norton start to scan things.
	Suddenly it takes 25 seconds for each keystroke to render on the screen. Why
	does it seem like I never suffer from that with my non work computers? Ah, I
	know why.
    </action>
    
    <action title="No one likes all the security patches" anchor="patches">
        MS computers usually need to be patched and rebooted monthly to stay secure.
	There are plenty of other operating systems out there that seem to avoid this.
	Thru obscurity you retort?  Maybe, but it's still annoying.
    </action>

    <action title="Microsoft SQL Server" anchor="mssql">
        Don't get me wrong... it's a great product. I've developed on it for a long time
	now. But can we please, please stop calling it: "sequel"
	<br/><br/>
	It should be wrong somehow for Microsoft to brand their product off of a language.
	I know, I'm gunna release my next application and name it:
	<literal>C#</literal>, or <literal>TCP/IP</literal>
	<br/><br/>
	It's cool to say that your product <literal>is a SQL server</literal>, but it's
	not cool to say <literal>it's SQL</literal>. SQL is a language, not a database engine!
    </action>

    <action title="MSDN search is poopy" anchor="msdn">
        As dominant as Microsoft is, and as much as you pay for their products
	I would like to think their web based support was better. Try searching
	for "xsl find last element in node" on:
	<list>
	    <element>
	        <link uri="http://search.microsoft.com/us/dev/" target="_blank">
	            search.microsoft.com/us/dev/
		</link>
	    </element>
	    <element>
	        <link uri="http://google.com" target="_blank">
		    google.com
		</link>
	    </element>
	</list>
	and compare the results. Which one does a better job of pointing you towards
	an example of how to print the last element of an XML node using XSL? I guess
	it's not fair to compare Google and Microsoft, it's just annoying how hard it
	can be to find support on Microsoft's site (remembering I paid them for it)
    </action>

    <action title="Dotnet typing" anchor="typing">
        Sure being strongly typed is good, and sure loose typing can be nice... but this
		is just wrong(vb.net): 
		<code>
Dim a As String
If a = "" and a Is Nothing Then
    Response.Write("wtf?")
End If
		</code>
    </action>

	<action title="Filesystem searching" anchor="nogrep">
		One day I was getting a dotnet exception where "something" was looking
		for a particular version of a DLL that I don't have.  I needed to determine
		what DLL was the culprit.  My first instinct was to search thru the 
		vb.net project files to see which one had a reference to the offending
		DLL.  I'll walk you thru it:
		<list>
			<element>
				Search for *.vbproj from the root of C
			</element>
			<element>
				Wait for it to pull back the results
			</element>
			<element>
				Copy the search results to another directory for full
				text searching
			</element>
			<element>
				Receive: "Cannot copy file: Cannot read from the source
				file or disk"
			</element>
			<element>
				Search again, this time also specifying the "word or
				phrase" as part of the search criteria
			</element>
			<element>
				Note start time: 10:32:48
			</element>
			<element>
				Get some coffee...
			</element>
			<element>
				Results come back: 10:34:59
			</element>
			<element>
				Wonder if: "Search is complete. There are no results to
				display" is accurate or not
			</element>
			<element>
				Send a particular .vbproj file to notepad to pull out
				text that's assuredly there...
			</element>
			<element>
				Search again, this time knowing that > 0 results should be found
			</element>
			<element>
				Note start time: 10:37:01
			</element>
			<element>
				Results come back: 10:38:10
			</element>
			<element>
				Wonder if: "Search is complete. There are no results to
				display" is accurate or not
			</element>
			<element>
				Do search again, using the exact file name as the target
				of the search, and also use the version [1.1.5000.27677]
				as the "word or phrase" (which I know is in the file)
			</element>
			<element>
				Wonder if: "Search is complete. There are no results to
				display" is accurate or not
			</element>
			<element>
				Start to get really frustrated
			</element>
			<element>
				Try to brainstorm on how to get access to grep, as Cygwin
				isn't installed, and I'm not allowed to install it
			</element>
			<element>
				Search for *.vbproj again. Then try to copy results
				[excluding shortcuts] to another folder
			</element>
			<element>
				Receive: "Cannot copy file: Cannot read from the source
				file or disk"
			</element>
			<element>
				Wonder if Visual Studio 2005 somwhow has a lock on one of the
				project files I'm trying to copy
			</element>
			<element>
				Close VS2005 (takes about 2 minutes to close)
			</element>
			<element>
				Realize the copy problem is being caused by the search
				results containing many references to .vbproj files by
				the same name. You may wonder how this can happen? Try
				"branching" with Microsoft's Team Foundation Server -
				each branch must have it's own directory to hold the
				working copy. You can't just "switch" to another branch
				using a single working copy.
			</element>
			<element>
				Starting to run out of ideas...
			</element>
			<element>
				Give up, mount the filesystem via another computer and
				immediately find what I was looking for:
				<code>
# find //host/d\$/projects/ -name *.vbproj -exec grep "1.0.5000.26660: {} \;
				</code>
				You might notice that I used Cygwin, not a Linux box. I
				did this only as an excercise to get to the data I
				needed using only Windows. In fact I had to reboot from
				the Gentoo partition of my laptop to the win32 partition
				simply to get what I needed using <i>only</i> Windows.
			</element>
			<element>*sigh*</element>
			
		</list>
	</action>
	
    <!-- 
    <action title="" anchor="">
        <code></code>
    </action>
    -->
        
</guide>
