<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/howto.xsl"?>
<guide created="08/24/2004">
    <author email="john.mcfarlane@rockfloat.com">John McFarlane</author>
    <abstract title="Openoffice.org - setup of default template">
        This document will go step by step thru the process of setting up a default
        template. This will allow all oo documents to start off with the fonts you
        prefer to use.
    </abstract> 
    <convention>OpenOffice will be referred to as oo in this howto</convention>
    <convention>This howto assumes you have a working copy of oo</convention>
    <change date="08/24/2004 @21:00">Initial creation</change>

    <action title="Open a new oo writer document" anchor="new_oo_doc">
    	Open up oo writer, which will present you with a blank
	document. If you do not know how to do this, you prolly need
	to learn how to install and configure oo first. 
    </action>
    <action title="Change the appearance to your liking" anchor="style">
        Next you need to use the stylist to begin working on your default
        template.  Hit F11 on your keyboard to view the stylelist.
        The stylelist is used to pick global styles per document.
        <image uri="oo_stylist.png" /><br/>
        
        The default style used for any oo writer document is determined by
        the "default" style.  In the stylelist look for the Default
        Paragraph Style and right click on it.  Choose "Modify" and
        select your preferred choices (this can include font, size,
        color, ect.)
    </action>

    <action title="Save the template of the document that is now to your liking" anchor="save_template">
        Next go to the oo File Menu and pick File::Templates::Save <p/>
        You will be presented with a dialog where you can specify the
        name of the template you want, hit "OK" when finished
        <image uri="oo_template_save.png" /><br/>
    </action>
    
    <action title="Tell oo to use this newly saved template for all new writer documents" anchor="use_template">
    	Go to the oo File Menu and pick File::Templates::Organize <p/>
	Double click on "Default" in the left pane, and then highlight
	the template you named earler.  Then go to Commands::Set as
	Default Template
        <image uri="oo_template_organize.png" /><br/>
    </action>
    
    <action title="Finish up and test" anchor="finish">
        Now you can click "Close Template Organizer" and close the oo document.
        All finished, open a fresh oo document and you'll find your preferences are now
        the default  :)
    </action>
    
    <!--
    <action title="" anchor="">
        <code></code>
    </action>
    -->    
</guide>
